Hello! In this episode of Bug Bounty Reports
Explained, I will show you an amazing,
out of the box hacking technique that could lead
to compromising anyone who uses Homebrew Casks to
install stuff on MacOS or Linux. The vulnerability
was found by RyotaK. Link to his blogpost is in
the description. Enjoy! Homebrew is a package
manager for MacOS - something like apt for Linux.
To install a cask, you run this command. Cask
was originally an independent brew extension
but now it's quite integrated with the tool.
At the moment, there are almost 4,000 casks.
Each is defined by a file which looks like this
and is stored in the official homebrew repository
on GitHub. Among other properties, there was
version of the cask and its checksum. You can
imagine that managing manually updates of 4,000
casks is a very time-consuming job. So homebrew
team automated it using GitHub Actions. It's
a platform integrated with GitHub for handling
things like running tests or deploying your code.
In Homebrew, there was a script that automatically
merged the pull request if it only changed the
version and the checksum of the cask. Let's
consider an attack scenario where we would like
to inject our code into a cask configuration file.
Although it's mostly used for storing static
information, it's still a ruby file so injecting
code here would lead to an RCE on the machine of
anyone who installs the cask. But before that your
pull request had to go through multiple checks.
Some of the requirements like modifying only one
file or not moving, creating or deleting files are
easy to meet and we will not focus on them here.
Two rules that are most relevant for us are that
count of added and deleted lines must be the same
and all changed lines must match these regexes.
So only versions and checksums could be changed.
At this point, you might be thinking that it's
yet another bug that originates from an incomplete
regex but it's not. It's much more interesting.
Instead, it's another case where security of
millions of users relies on a relatively small
repository that it will do what it's supposed todo.
Because to know what were the changes in the
files, GitHub Actions script used this git_diffrepository.
Because you can run `git diff` command
but it only returns text and to know if the pull
request should be auto merged or not, you must
know exactly what was inside the commits.
git_diff is a ruby library that parses the text from `git
diff` command and returns concrete information
about how many files were changed, what were
those files and what were those changes and so on.
The hunter decided to try to hide malicious
changes from this git_diff script. It takes
the input from `git diff` command and it's using
text parsing and regexes to extract information.
This is an example `git diff`
after changing one line in a file.
Importantly, even though the file was still in
the same location, `git diff` prints those file
names with a/ or b/ prepended to differentiate
between versions of the file. So git_diff library
first parsed this first line, it also checked if
any files were added or deleted and so on and soon...
There were quite a lot of regexes like this.
But for us, the interesting part starts here.
If the line starts with +++ followed by
b/filepath, it means that the following changes
added lines to this file. If it starts with
--- followed by a/filepath, it means those
lines were deleted from this file. Then, there
is information about those lines and then there
are contents of the file. If the line is not
prepended by anything, it means it's unchanged.
If there is a minus it means it was deleted
and if there was a plus it means it was added.
Now, let's see what happens when I make
this change - where I add a line that starts
with ++. It was an added line so in `git diff` one
plus sign is prepended before this line. It looks
like this and we can see by the color that
it was added to the file. However, git_diff
ruby library did not work on colors
- it only saw the raw text input.
So when seeing this output, it didn't consider it
an added line but instead, it matched this regex.
So git_diff thought it's an information that some
lines were added to this file but since there are
no lines that were actually changed, so no lines
prepended by a single minus or a single plus,
it detects 0 file changes. This gives you the
ability to add almost arbitrary lines to ruby
files in the official Homebrew repository. Almost
arbitrary because there were still a few problems.
First, line in the file must
start with a double plus sign.
What does it mean in ruby? Not much actually. Plus
and minus before a variable act as just sign of a
number. So if you have a positive number, putting
a minus in front of it will make it negative.
But putting a plus, two minuses or two
pluses will not affect it. Importantly,
it will not throw an error, even if the expression
is a string. Another problem that you must solve
is that the changed file must be inside Casks/
folder. When git_diff library sees multiple lines,
the next one overrides the previous one so you can
have anything you want in the first line as long
as the second will match this regex which will
be a file inside Casks/ folder. Unfortunately,
it's still not the end - it's only half of the
problems. Because due to another bug in git_diff,
the line with the filename must not use quotes.
When ruby sees this code, it tries to evaluate
variable b, variable Casks and then call
the rb function on the variable iterm2.
To avoid exceptions of undefined objects, here
the hunter defined all these in the previous line.
This is the syntax in ruby which you can use to
embed ruby code inside a string. And finally,
the last problem that you have to solve is
Rubocop - a static code analyzer and formatter.
It didn't quite like the style of the injected
code. It knows that exploits must be elegant.
Although you could disable it in one line by
adding a comment, you couldn't use that in
the second line because then it was parsed as
the part of the filename. What the hunter did
was adding a third line in between with
an if instruction and the comment. Then,
the next slide was treated as the part of the
if expression and Rubocop also ignored it. This
is the final payload. With approval of the
Homebrew security team, the pull request
was approved and the change was merged to
iterm2 cask which is the second most popular.
It actually worked too well because not only was
this printed during the installation of this one
cask but also during the cleanup so some users
noticed that immediately. The change was quickly
reverted and the bug was triaged. Homebrew
only has a vulnerability disclosure program
so no bounty was awarded for this report.
As for the fix, review and automerge actions
are no longer in the repository. That's it for
this video. If you are a member of BBRE Premium,
check out the member platform because
soon, I will publish hands-on labs and
you will be able to practice this vulnerability
yourself. If you'd like to subscribe check out
premium.bugbountyexplained.com. Anyway if you've
learned something new today, leave a like and
recommend this video to someone who will also like
this. For now, thank you for watching and goodbye!